This video is sponsored by Planet Wild.
They're essentially crowdfunding for
nature. Every month their community
funds a new nature protection mission
and they document it through videos on
YouTube. But more on that later.
There's not a single person in the world
that knows how to make this toaster.
I know that might seem impossible, but
it's true. Let me explain.
In 2011, British designer and writer
Thomas Thwaites tried to build a toaster
from scratch. Nothing crazy, just a
simple electric toaster equivalent to
any cheap one you can find at a
department store.
He figured, especially with his design
experience, how hard could it be?
Turns out, for one person, it's
impossible.
When he bought and opened a toaster to
base his own on, Thwaites was
immediately distraught. [music]
Despite it being a cheap $6 toaster,
there were 400 parts made of more than
100 different materials. How was he
possibly going to acquire or make all
the materials and parts needed? He had
little to no idea where to obtain things
like iron ore, plastic, copper, and
rubber. And so he began talking to
professors and experts, reading up on
the history and logistics of various
kinds of material sourcing and
manufacturing.
Over the following 9 months, Thwaites
found himself on [music] an obscure
journey across industries, the world,
and history.
He got copper from an abandoned mine on
the island of Anglesey in Wales,
obtained iron ore from Clearwell Caves
in England, and then tried to smelt it
using a homemade furnace, extracted mica
off mountains in Scotland, and attempted
to make plastic from potato starch in
his backyard.
In the end, after 9 months and thousands
of dollars, Thwaites essentially had
nothing in the form of a fully
functioning toaster. [music]
He couldn't figure out how to make
rubber from scratch, so the wires had no
insulation and after 5 seconds of the
toaster being plugged in and ran, the
heating element melted itself.
Thwaites' entire experiment, which would
come to be known as The Toaster Project,
was inspired by a scene in Douglas
Adams' novel series The Hitchhiker's
Guide to the Galaxy, where a 20th
century man finds himself stranded on a
planet with technologically primitive
people.
He assumes that with his experience with
advanced technology, he'll be able to
become a kind of emperor of the planet
and transform its conditions.
Instead, he soon realizes
although he originally came from [music]
a world which had cars and computers and
ballet and Armagnac, he didn't by
himself know how any of it worked. He
couldn't do it. Left to his own devices,
he couldn't build a toaster.
>> [music]
>> He could just about make a sandwich and
that was it.
Without the rest of modern society, the
intricate network of people, knowledge,
and systems, [music]
each with their own essential node in
the process of civilization and its
products, the man really couldn't do
much of anything in the modern
technological sense.
The Wait project showed that this is
also true for each [music] of us on this
planet right now.
Think about every object you use on a
daily basis. From simple household items
like forks, bottles, and couches, to
intricate devices like phones,
computers, [music]
cars, and toasters.
Every single one of them have massive
intricate lineages of conception,
[music] design, production, and
distribution required for them to wind
up in each of our hands and homes.
As individuals, not only understanding
but carrying out the complete process of
production for any object or technology,
let alone all the objects we use, would
be impossible.
With exception to simple primitive
tools, we would not accomplish much of
anything on our own.
Consider that in the case of a simple
toaster, the copper for the wiring might
be mined in Chile, processed in China,
[music] and then sent elsewhere for
assembly. The nickel that makes up the
heating element might be mined in
Indonesia and then sent to China to be
refined. The iron ore might be mined in
Australia, which still needs to be
smelted into iron, refined into steel,
and then fabricated into the parts that
make up the toaster's body and frame.
This goes for every part and material of
the 400 plus parts that make up a simple
toaster.
Hundreds, if not thousands of
individuals, are essential to the
process. Miners, designers, engineers,
chemists, manufacturers, business
operators, deliverers, and so on.
Most of whom only know how to carry out
their part of the process.
Almost everything you use and touch on
an average day is a kind of miracle
forged out of the material of the earth
and the human mind.
Human engineering facilitated by vast
networks of manufacturing, brought to
you by carefully orchestrated
distribution channels, all of which
originated from human thoughts and
ideas.
In the words of poet John Donne,
"No man is an island entire of itself.
Every man is a piece of the continent, a
part of the main."
The beginning of everything.
One thing that Dwight discovered that is
even more interesting and potentially
existential crisis inducing is that the
smaller the scale you want to work on,
the further back in time you have to go.
Every man-made object and technology is
not only connected to the web of modern
industry, but also to the web of human
history.
The history of everything. [music]
Every new idea, every new design, every
new object and technology is built on
the back of prior ideas, [music]
designs, and technologies, all the way
back to the first and simplest ideas and
[music] technologies.
Man learned to create fire hundreds of
thousands of years ago,
>> [music]
>> so that now we can toast slices of bread
equally on both sides at the same time.
[music]
One does not exist without the other.
Nothing exists without everything that
led to it.
But where did everything come from to
begin with?
Where did it all start?
Humanity itself does not exist in a
vacuum. [music]
We are a species in the context of
nature and evolution and the world. And
yet we are apparently alone in creating
fire, forging swords, constructing
buildings, flying planes, and building
[music] computers and digital
intelligence systems, and everything
else.
But why is this the case? Why and how
did humanity separate so significantly
from the apparent nature of everything
else?
The answer is, in large part, found in
one of the most unsuspecting and almost
humorous places.
The thumb.
The opposable appendage sticking out the
sides of each of our hands.
By appearance alone, the opposable thumb
might seem to be a modest biological
mutation.
But this little appendage changed the
world completely, allowing for a whole
new realm of existence.
All the networks of civilization that we
experience today, every technology and
man-made object, the state of the world,
our endless yearn made tangible, is, in
large part, the product of this thing on
our hands.
With it, brought almost everything else.
The thumb brain.
In 2025, a study out of the University
of Reading in the UK titled Human
Dexterity and Brains Evolved Hand in
Hand, explored the relationship between
the size of opposable thumbs
>> [music]
>> and the size of brains.
The researchers analyzed nearly 100
living and fossil primate species,
including humans, chimpanzees, gorillas,
orangutans, macaques, [music]
and other ancient hominid species.
What they found surprised them.
Longer thumbs not only appeared to have
a correlation with larger brain sizes,
but the part of the brain that is
bigger, relative to longer thumbs, is
the neocortex.
The part of the brain responsible for
higher-order functions, like conscious
[music] thought, sensory perception,
spatial reasoning, and complex language.
This suggests that these two things
potentially grow together. The thumb and
the neocortex.
On the face of it, this might seem kind
of absurd. How or why would the thumb
have any direct relationship with
consciousness, with language, and with
the complexity of thought?
Though certainly bizarre, after
examining it further,
>> [music]
>> it makes a lot of sense.
Without thumbs in some form, we wouldn't
be able to meaningfully create or engage
in anything that requires gripping,
grasping, holding, or pinching.
This includes early primitive tools like
hammer stones, axes, [music] sticks, and
spears.
If humans never evolved thumbs, these
tools would likely have never existed in
the forms they did, and tools would have
likely remained extremely simplistic.
[music]
Consider the tools of other species
without opposable thumbs. Crows bend and
shape twigs, finches use cactus spines,
[music]
otters use rocks, and elephants direct
branches with their trunks.
All of which is extremely simplistic,
[music] imprecise, and limited.
This, of course, matters a lot. If human
tools remained equally imprecise and
primitive, then early humans would have
been less precise in what they could do
and build with such tools. And if humans
were less precise and [music] more
simplistic in their interfacing with the
world, then the mental modeling required
to engage with tools in the world would
have also remained more simplistic and
minimal.
A species doesn't need complex terms and
conceptual modeling for a world that
they poke and smash.
But for a world that comprises
increasing intricacy and strategy, it
does.
Complex tools seem to apply a kind of
pressure on the brain to expand.
As the possibility and complexity of
tools increase, so too must cognition.
And as cognition increases, so too can
the complexity [music] of tools.
What seems to be the result of a limited
ability to grasp and grip isn't a slower
development of tools, but it results in
them never really getting off the ground
floor. And consciousness thus never
really expands, [music] and civilization
never begins.
But of course, we did evolve thumbs.
We learned to grasp, [music] grip,
pinch, and create. We created axes and
hammer stones, then spears and bow
arrows, then plows and the written
[music] word, then cars and planes and
computers.
Each of these creations expanded the
[music] possibilities and needs of the
human species.
At each point, the complexity of our
relationship with the world grew. And at
each point, so too did our cognitive
abilities, creating a feedback loop
where every cognitive enhancement has
led to a greater ability to create more
advanced [music] tools and technologies,
which continues to lead to cognitive
enhancements,
so on and [music] so forth.
What have we done?
In the early 1890s, there were new
campus buildings being constructed at
Ohio State University.
>> [music]
>> As part of the new developments, a large
central grass space was created that
would come to be known as the Oval.
For years, there were no official
walkways in the Oval,
>> [music]
>> just an open field. As students began
walking across the grass to get to and
from different buildings, however,
>> [music]
>> they began choosing specific routes that
were shortest or most convenient.
Soon, [music] dirt trails began to
appear on these routes as the students
wore the grass down from frequent
walking.
>> [music]
>> Then, even more students began to walk
the same routes, now with the addition
of a visual trail.
These worn-down trails are what are
known as desire paths. [music]
They appear all over the world in
cities, campuses, and parks for similar
reasons.
By the early 1900s at Ohio State
University, the university based their
placement of concrete sidewalks in the
Oval off these desire [music] paths.
The outcome was a strange asymmetrical
pattern of sidewalks sprawling across
the grass field,
>> [music]
>> each path meeting at certain centers and
connection points, all together creating
a kind of webbing of apparent random
connectivity forged by [music] the
continual patterns of human desire and
goals.
We so often feel like we are choosing we
are going, what we are doing, and why.
[music]
But history is a desired path.
The world is a network of these
apparently random connections
>> [music]
>> forged by the patterns of human desire
and goals.
Through which we each walk every day and
every moment.
The development of tools and
technologies don't merely affect how we
tangibly interact with the world, but
also how we understand and think about
it abstractly.
We each not only arrive with our thumbs,
but we arrive with our particular
cognitive models of the world, a
particular size of the neocortex,
[music] and an understanding of
phenomena developed and facilitated by a
state of technology and a corresponding
[music] state of culture.
Thumbs did not merely lead to spears,
spoons, writing, toasters, and cell
phones, but they also in some meaningful
sense led to the creation of [music]
religions, of philosophies, of
ideologies, of beliefs.
Where does everything go from here?
Before thumbs, [music]
animals couldn't grasp or grip the
world. Thumbs evolved as a way to
literally do this, to gain greater
control over the world and its inherent
chaos and uncertainty.
>> [music]
>> But ironically, through what thumbs have
allowed us to do and create and
understand,
>> [music]
>> we have mostly discovered how little
control we can ever have over anything.
We have built an unfathomably complex
civilization, cultures and industries,
ideologies and religions and
philosophies, math and science. We have
created fire and toasters and
smartphones, all to have no control over
or understanding of the very things and
systems we built.
The modern world is a kind of
self-propelling network of desires
formed from the walking paths of the
humans and species before us.
Modern industry and culture move
forward, producing new technologies and
new ideas that appear in our hands, in
our homes, and our minds.
And yet, we never really can see or
understand the complete [music] process
of any of it. Where it all comes from,
how it's made, and why.
Ultimately, each of our existences are a
network of contingencies [music]
that no one person or group ever had a
say in, ever started, or can ever fully
understand or take control of.
Our beliefs and ideas are really not so
dissimilar from a toaster, made of
hundreds if not thousands of parts and
materials sourced from all over the
world and tracing deep into history.
What would we have been without thumbs?
What would the world have become?
Perhaps something entirely alien to us.
Or perhaps something incredibly basic
and simple.
We'll never know.
But we can know that the world that we
have created appears [music] entirely
alien to everything else in the cosmos.
A beautiful and terrifying array of
technological and cognitive possibility,
of desire and need, of good and bad, of
intelligence and [music] ignorance.
We don't know where we are going or why.
We don't know why the whole process
started. We don't know what our thumbs
and minds will hold next.
But in any and every moment, we can know
just how absurd and improbable holding
anything [music] is. From the simplest
to the grandest of moments and objects.
For a toaster to arrive on your counter,
>> [music]
>> for a pen to arrive in your drawer, for
shoes to arrive on your feet, a phone in
your pocket, a concept in your mind,
and a thumb on your hand.
Through our thumbs and minds, we have
[music] changed the world completely.
This is no doubt equated to many
miraculous things, but it is also
equated to many devastating things. We
must use our thumbs and minds, our
capabilities and power, as much as we
[music] do to create and innovate, to
help preserve and protect this planet,
to undo damage we've done, and to help
nature in ways that only we as humans
can.
That's one of the reasons why I joined
Planet Wild and why I'm so thrilled to
be partnering with them for this video.
Planet Wild is a community-based nature
protection organization that makes it
possible for each of us to help protect
nature. Every month, its community of
more than 25,000 members, including
myself, funds a new carefully selected
mission, like restoring forests,
bringing back endangered species, and
protecting oceans. In under 30 days, you
can see your impact as Planet Wild
shares update videos right here on
YouTube. You can also observe the
interactive map on the app and get
insights on data and funding [music] and
earn badges for your contributions. What
I love about Planet Wild is that you can
feel and see your impact directly. It's
not just an occasional email. It's a
community that you participate in and
watch develop. One recent mission
involved helping restore the world's
largest tropical lake, Lake Victoria.
[music]
This lake supports around 45 million
people and over 600 freshwater species.
Right [music] next to it is a forest
that helps support it, which has been
severely degraded over recent years.
Planet Wild is helping reverse this by
planting 80,000 [music] trees and
funding the necessary tech to make sure
the forest and surrounding ecosystem can
thrive long-term.
Perhaps one of the most impressive feats
humanity has ever accomplished, of which
Planet Wild is at the forefront, is
bringing nature back to life. Help us
continue to do this with Planet Wild by
scanning the QR code or clicking the
link in the description. As a special
gift, the first 100 people to sign up
using my code, pursuit8, will get their
first month paid for by me. You can
cancel anytime.
Give whatever amount you can, big or
small. And if you want to see Planet
Wild in action, check out their mission
at Lake Victoria, linked below.
And of course, as always, [music]
thank you so much for watching in
general, and see you next video.
>> Hey.